This was
our example.
We would like to implement
this in a state diagram.
And on this I will then
explain the individual basic elements of statecharts.
We'll start by
modeling the minute display.
We have
to start somewhere.
We have hours,
minutes, the alarm state.
Any of these we
have to model first.
State diagrams allow
us, in UML
terms, to develop just individual components of
the overall state space step by step.
And we start with the minute
display or actually the minute counter.
There are 60
minute states: from 0-59.
And there we can
first imagine that this is
still a little bit
like a flat state diagram.
But later it will appear
nested in a larger state diagram.
And then it
won't be nested anymore.
So first of all, just
intuitively, what's the syntax here?
One difference to
flat statecharts is
that there are very special
ways to represent the states.
Here there
are these states.
These would be these
rectangles with rounded edges here.
These would be the simplest
states that you can have.
We have a name,
here simply numbered (0-59).
That should
be unique.
And in between
there are transitions.
Transitions can be
annotated with a label.
That's what's
called a trigger.
So we
have states.
We
have transitions.
These arrows, there can be a trigger
on them, that is, a triggering event.
That can take
different shapes, we'll see.
And what we have here
specifically is the start state.
It looks like
this in activity diagrams.
This is what in
a flat state diagram
would just be the incoming
arrow to the start state.
We start
counting at zero.
Counting up to 59,
each time after 1 minute.
Because that's supposed to be the
minute display, and then return to zero.
And then it goes
on and on like that.
So what are
the elements here?
States, they
are these depictions.
Start state is represented
by this special start node,
which looks like it
does on activity charts.
From there there is an arrow
to one of the normal states.
No edges may lead
into this special element.
And only one
edge may lead out.
This is different from
the activity diagram, where
several edges are allowed to
come out of this element.
Simple
elements.
Then there can also
be an end state.
This does not appear
in the example yet.
End states are also
noted, as in activity
diagram, with this
kind of depiction.
The flow end does not
exist in correspondence to activity diagrams.
But this way to
indicate the end state.
And similar to
activity diagram also, no
edges are allowed to
lead out of these elements.
Unlike start states, there may
well be multiple end states.
Such a thing can appear
several times in a state
diagram, while there can
be only one start state.
Or later only one
per level or subdivided substate.
And in fact, this
is what is considered the
final state here, rather
than the state before it.
It can also be, as in our example,
that there are no final states at all.
This is the case when we
want to model a system that is
not supposed to
terminate at all.
It should run on and
on and not stop somewhere.
That is why there
is no final state there.
Then there is the
notation for these transitions/arrows.
In the simplest case simply
this connection with an arrow.
These are
also called transitions.
On the one
hand this is a
bit awkward, because in Petri
nets transitions already have a meaning.
But it is the case
that the same term is used.
And it is not
so completely detached or
completely different from the concept
of transitions in Petri nets.
It is also about creating
a mediation between two states.
In the Petri net between two places,
or the transport of marks between places.
But a transition
is simply this arrow.
And not some extra node, as
it was the case in Petri nets.
In general there is
a label on this arrow.
That's where the
trigger can be.
We have already seen
that, such a triggering event.
Or simply
a label.
There can
also be conditions.
These can
be logical statements.
A bit like in activity
diagram with the branching nodes.
And there can
be an effect.
We'll see what's involved there in a
moment, and how we can use that.
These two parts
are optional, though.
We just had
triggers in the example.
There was
this statement:
"After 1 minute, there should
be a transition at a time."
The trigger would be something
like a signal or a message
that triggers
the corresponding transition.
So causing
that transition.
In this case the
passing of 1 minute.
At the condition can
be something supervising, a guard.
And it can depend on different properties
of the system, what can occur there.
We will
use Guard less.
use effect, though.
That is generally something
that triggers this transition.
We will see later that this
can then trigger transitions in other parts
of the state
diagram, for example.
In the example so far, the
minutes display, there is only the trigger.
Simply this specification of a period of
time after which the transition has to trigger.
Later, this trigger can also be
something that was triggered as an
effect in another part
of the state chart.
We will see this after
a few more observations and slides.
There will rather be no label
at the arrow from the start
state, but really only at
the transitions between normal states.
Not at
the start state.
At arrows to the final state
there could well be such labeling.
But primarily we will have that
at the transition between normal simple states.
Then there are actions
or effects that can occur.
Not at the transition between
states, but in the states themselves.
Until now, a state was simply
a box with no other internal shape.
In fact, in
the UML state diagram,
actions can be triggered
in the simple states themselves.
Or activities
can be annotated.
Which should be triggered
respectively when entering, when staying
in the state,
or when leaving.
We will use this in a moment
for the beeping in our state diagram.
In principle, the structure of these is
the same as the labeling of transitions.
There can be a trigger, there can
be conditions, there can be an effect.
The trigger here
is something that describes
at what time
this effect should occur.
Namely exactly this: when
entering, when staying, during leaving.
That means the trigger
can take these three forms.
So the effect, which is written
here, is triggered when entering the state.
An activity should take place while
the system remains in this state.
Or something should happen when
the system leaves the state.
Activity is to be understood here
quite in the sense of activity diagrams.
This could be,
for example, that
an activity diagram is embedded
in such a state diagram.
That is supposed to run while
the overall system is in said state.
We will
not do that.
We will not
use this possibility.
But it would
be possible in principle.
We will rather
use only simple effects.
In particular, in
our example we said:
There should be a sound
signal, and always on the hour.
We can model
that, for example,
by saying there is
this activity called "beep".
That's not
specified further.
This is simply an activity
that is perhaps described separately.
We don't give
any further structure here.
And it should be triggered
whenever the state zero is entered.
What before was just
this very simple state, rectangle
with rounded corners,
where 0 was inside.
Now it gets
an inner structure.
This is noted in such a way
that there is still the label zero.
And also the outer form is
still this rectangle with rounded corners.
But in the state
inside is still annotated:
Whenever the state is entered, the
effect/activity sound signal should be triggered.
I.e. we need a
syntax for these states.
Unlike flat state diagrams, where states
were simply nodes with a name.
And nothing else
could happen in there.
That would be
the minute display.
Along with the beeping whenever the
zero state, the 0 minutes are entered.
What about
the hour display?
For those, of course, we
could do the same thing again.
Instead of 60 such simple states for the minutes,
there would then be 24 states for the hours.
Now, of course, we want
this to happen in parallel.
We want that there is always 1
minute and 1 hour at each time.
The naive approach would then be to
say we have to form the cross product.
From the set of all minutes 0-59
and the set of all hours 0-24.
Then each state would be a
pair of one minute and one hour.
This is exactly what is also
visible here in such a display.
Here is finally a pair from a
number of hours and a number of minutes.
But 24 × 60 that would be already
very many such pairs, which one can form.
We do
not want that.
Instead, we want to explicitly express that
minutes and hour display run in parallel.
That is, the clock is
always in two such states
without us actually having
to form these pairs.
Let it be expressed in such a way that the
clock is always in two states at the same time.
In an hour state
and a minute state.
That didn't exist in
the flat state diagram.
One way
to express that.
Here
there is.
And that is modeled
by what are called regions.
Regions are simply a way
to divide a state diagram
into at least two (possibly more)
areas that run parallel to each other.
So that the system is then in
a sub-state in each of these regions.
Our example will
just allow this
to have 24 hours and 60
minutes of states running in parallel.
We would then
have to plot 84
states instead of explicitly making
all pairs between hours and minutes.
Which would result in over
1000 states by cross product.
Which is why these
regions are also semantically much
more effective than areas
of the activity diagrams.
Where I had said, we draw those
in to get a grouping of actions.
But beyond that, they
don't have any particular meaning.
With regions in state diagrams, what
those do is really very effective.
Namely, that the state diagram is
actually always, in that case, two
states at
the same time.
In each
region in one.
Because it corresponds to parallelism, it
has rather a bit of the
character that you get
with activity diagrams by forking.
These regions are parallel in the sense
that there are no transitions between them.
If two regions are parallel,
there can be no transitions
that move from a state of one
region, to a state of the other region.
I cannot come in
the from a minute state
by some trigger
into an hour state.
What can happen, on the other
hand, is that minutes and hours counters
progress in parallel
at the same time.
So if a trigger occurs in
both regions, it can also cause state
changes in both regions in
one step at the same time.
But there is no
transition between two parallel transitions.
There can be a transition from one
region to a region not parallel to it.
So a region shown completely
somewhere else in the state diagram.
But not between two
or more parallel regions.
How does this turn
out for our clock example?
How are
these regions plotted?
As
follows.
What we have now is that we
decompose the overall system into two regions.
That's expressed by
this dividing line.
So we would now have a region
up here and a region down here.
And each of these two regions
is its own little state diagram.
That's where we
see at the bottom.
What was previously
under entire state diagram,
for the minute counter, is now
simply one of the two parallel regions.
And the other region
looks something like this.
But has fewer states, because
it's just about the hours.
Which is only
24, instead of 60.
We also see that there is now one
start state in each of the two parts.
There can be a separate
start state in each region.
In both cases
just the zero state.
Once for the hours
once for the minutes.
We also see that
names may be reused here.
That's okay because
they're in different regions.
So this zero cannot be
confused with this zero, etc.
It's just within a region that a name
is not allowed to appear more than once.
And what you also see is that
here, of course, other triggers are assigned.
We don't want to change the
hour state after 1 minute as well.
Instead, we want an hour transition
to occur when trigger h is fired.
Where does
this come from?
Well, we will discuss
that in a moment.
It will be triggered whenever 1
hour is full in the minutes region.
So at the transition from 59 minutes to
0 minutes again there is 1 hour transition.
Which then simultaneously causes a
progression in the hours count.
This is a
communication between two regions.
But not by transitions, so an
arrow that would cross this regions border.
But by
this "remote triggering"
of an effect, which corresponds to
a trigger in the other region.
A few
more remarks.
Some of them
I had already discussed.
First, there are
two start states.
There can be at
most one per region.
That's exactly what we've
taken advantage of here.
We have exactly
one in each region.
That means overall the logical start
state would be 0 hours 0 minutes.
Time
00:00.
And hour and minute
indicators do not work independently.
Parallel, but
not completely independent.
There
is synchronization.
Namely, exactly when
in the minute part
there is a transition to the minute
state zero, this triggers the effect h.
For hour (hour) this
is supposed to stand.
This effect h ensures as
a trigger in the parallel regions
that the hours
are counted up.
This takes
place simultaneously.
In each region
we have this transition.
This allows us to express here
in a meaningful coupled way what
it means to have
hours and minutes progress.
That covers part
of our target implementation.
That ultimately describes
how time evolves.
Then there's this
aspect of alarm setting.
We would like to add to
our state diagram the ability to
turn off and on
that hourly alarm signal.
So obviously there's
like an extra state
for alarm is on, and an
extra state for alarm is off.
So where do
we put those now?
We don't want to tinker
those into those regions somehow.
Then we would
unnecessarily complicate that part
of the state diagram
that deals with time.
By also bringing in
this alarm on/off property here.
We would like
to be modular.
What we have so
far should still be usable.
And separately there should
be this alarm on/off possibility.
So imaginable we have
alarm on, alarm off.
Between them there
should be triggers.
By pressing the button
a you should get there.
And we should be able to switch between these
two states alarm on or alarm off by pressing b.
If we look at our stylized
picture of the clock, we see that
we would then need quite a
lot of transitions labeled with a.
Which would have to go out
from all possible hour and minute states.
If we have 00:00, then it
must be possible to switch a
to get into
the alarm display.
If we have 00:01, it
would also have to be possible.
Factually, for every combination
of hour and minute we
would have to have a-
transition to go into alarm state.
That would not
be very modular.
Since we wouldn't be able to
achieve that we would only need to
extend this state diagram minimally
to bring in this alarm aspect.
What can
we do instead?
There is a solution for that in the
UML state diagrams, that there are composite states.
Hierarchies of states where incoming and
outgoing transitions can then be captured.
Instead of having quite a lot of transitions
by the fact that for each combination of
the one composite state, we have to
have one transition each into another component.
It's very
abstract now.
Let's just look at
it in the example.
What we
can do:
We can take what we
have so far as our
time count as
one composite state.
And capture the alarm
aspect in another composite state.
There is the
time display here.
And that's
modeled this way.
And there's the alarm
display, it's modeled like this.
There is
on and off.
You can switch back and
forth between them with b.
And there is the button a, which switches
between the alarm situation and the time display.
That then corresponds to being able to
switch between the time and the alarm display.
And b is to switch between
on and off in the alarm display.
The advantage here is, we can just
use what we did for the hour count.
And describe as a
separate component this alarm component.
The one on the right,
what was previously our entire
state chart, is now
simply a composite state.
This on the left
is also a composite state.
This is the alarm display,
which consists of on and off.
There's a start state
for each everywhere here.
And there is also a start
state for the whole state diagram.
Initially the time display and not
the alarm display shall be activated.
These a-transitions shall
not start from sub-states,
but from the
whole composite state here.
This saves us the
otherwise necessary many a-labeled transitions.
Which we potentially,
otherwise would need.
Two
more comments.
First, the states with regions
are of course also composite.
And this is in the sense
that they are composed of region,
rather than
being hierarchically composed.
A regions state
is also composed,
but in a different way than
this state which is hierarchically composed.
Not by regions, but
simply by having multiple sub-states.
And to distinguish this more clearly,
in what follows I will generally, not
speak of composite
states in general.
Instead, rather of hierarchical states on the
one hand and regions states on the other.
Hierarchical states will be something like
what you see here on the left.
Just any
nested states.
This can also have
multiple levels of nesting.
Region states will be those
that consist of multiple regions.
So indicated with
such a dashed line.
And of course the regions themselves
can be composed of several sub-states.